http://www.alandavies.org/blog

alan@alandavies.org

Summary

I'm an experienced software engineer with excellent leadership and interpersonal skills as well as significant experience with client engagement. Although I didn't start out professionally as an engineer I've essentially been one ever since I was a kid. It just took me a while to finally do it professionally. I'm a geek at heart and best in a tactical capacity where I can be hands-on while also leading and mentoring a small team or working with clients. I'm a designer, builder, problem-solver, teacher, mentor, consultant and evangelist. I'm an incurably curious perfectionist who's just as much at home in a client presentation as chasing down a bug, designing a new system or optimizing some code.

Work Experience

FactSet Research Systems Inc.

1/2015 – 4/2019: Vice President, Principal Software Engineer, Database Infrastructure Norwalk, CT, USA

- Technical lead for all internal RDBMS infrastructure and related services
- Internal data consultant/architect/evangelist. Experienced with various database technologies: RDBMS (OLTP/OLAP/row/columnar), key-value, document, time-series, message queue, graph; scale-up and scale-out
- Provide consulting on data modelling, ETL, data pipelines, ingestion, transaction processing, reporting and more
- Lead a six-month research working group to vet commercial/open-source RDBMS technologies and select a standard for future internal use. Gained an in depth understanding of DB2, Oracle, PostgreSQL, SQL Server and MySQL/MariaDB
- Develop/support all internal RDBMS access/management APIs
- Wrote RDBMS training curricula. Deliver regular internal training programs and info sessions.
- Develop/manage/support a secure, elastic RDBMS proxy and multi-tenancy infrastructure
- Designed/built a custom CI/Test/CD system for all our group's internal products
- Code regularly in C#, PowerShell, SQL
- Regularly engage with external database technology vendors to vet and recommend internal technical direction
- Helped to develop FactSet's road map to move our application stack from our own data centres to public cloud
- Participated in several executive briefing/planning sessions at AWS and Microsoft

3/2012 – 1/2015: Vice President, Principal Software Engineer, Content Integration Engineering Norwalk, CT, USA

- Left management to lead an R&D project to design/build a new high-performance data-store/service for a specific dataset
- Researched scale-out columnar database technologies: Greenplum, Vertica, Hadoop, SAP Hanna, etc.
- Ultimately went with a custom solution with an in-memory data service backed by a SQL database. Designed, prototyped and led a team to build it. Features: Point-in-time data views, parallelized query execution, optimized data loads.
- Ported complex legacy C++ code (from acquisition) to C#. Lots of unit tests to verify logic.
- Adapted code from this project to create a generic versioned data caching layer for C#
- Authored a framework for the standardized management of SQL Server schema changes
- Engaged in several internal data architecture consulting projects for key constituencies across FactSet

12/2008 – 3/2012: Vice President, Associate Director, Content Integration Engineering Norwalk, CT, USA

- As part of a reorganization I shifted focus to lead content integration for various new high profile areas: reported company chart of accounts, analyst estimated company data, M&A, VC, ownership and private equity
- Dealt with attrition/morale issues after a significant reorganization. Identified new leaders and rebuilt teams.
- Built new working relationships with FactSet's growing inhouse content collection and collection engineering groups
- Led all engineering work related to the technology integration of a key acquisition
- Actively involved in the design of data feed methodologies for new FactSet data sets
- Established an initial offshore team in Manila. Developed a recruiting/training strategy with HR. Visited several times.
- Led a task force to focus on delivering major improvements in query performance for a high profile dataset. Lots of politics.

9/2004 – 12/2008: Vice President, Associate Director, Product Engineering Norwalk, CT, USA

- Moved to the US to lead International Database Engineering (Europe, Asia-Pac and a core of US activity too)
- Managed continued growth. Ultimately led a team of 30 across three regions including sub-managers.
- Drove several key infrastructure and product initiatives, and continued to lead the Internationalization (I18N) agenda

9/2001 - 9/2004: Head of Asia Pacific Engineering Tokyo, Japan I was asked to relocate to Tokyo and tasked with repeating the success of hiring database engineers in London Hired and trained a local Tokyo engineering team while also continuing to remotely manage London Database Engineering Re-architected the Asia-Pac databases and feed handlers to achieve significant improvements in reliability and performance Added several new data feed systems Managed vendor relations with various Asia-Pac data suppliers (stock exchanges, financial publishing companies) Initiated the effort to internationalize FactSet's codebase and ultimately deliver localized product Established the concept of an office-hours based geographically rotating "Engineer on Duty" to monitor key systems 12/1999 - 9/2001: Software Engineer, London London, UK Shifted over to Software Engineering to start to build the first non-US engineering team Hired and trained the first tier of London database engineers Personally developed several data feed systems. Built the first generation of generic data integration tools. 2/1999 - 12/1999: European Product Development, London London, UK Moved back to London to become the first representative of Product Development in Europe Worked extensively with several external data suppliers in order to host their data on the FactSet platform 4/1996 - 2/1999: Product Development, Greenwich Greenwich, CT, USA Requested a move to the US in order to join the nascent Product Development department Provided tier-2 support to clients. Worked with sales on custom client projects involving the FactSet API. Took many engineering classes at NYU. Taught myself C++ and actively started contributing code to the FactSet system. Product lead for the FactSet-Excel Link. Managed/developed several significant enhancements to Excel functionality. 4/1994 - 3/1996: Client Services / Sales Engineering London, UK Employee #3 in FactSet's London office. Part of the core team trying to establish FactSet's business in Europe. Worked extensively with prospects and clients in London, Zurich, Geneva & Paris

Technical Skills/Experience

Operating Systems	Windows, OpenVMS, Linux (RedHat, Ubuntu)	
Database Systems	SQL Server, PostgreSQL, MySQL/MariaDB, Oracle, Vertica, TigerGraph, Amazon Neptune, Couchbase	
Primary Languages	C#, C++, SQL, Perl; PowerShell, Bash	
Other	On-prem vs. cloud technologies (AWS/Azure), data structures and algorithms, data modelling, data warehousing, ETL, data scaling/sharding, test driven development, CI/CD, build systems, Perforce, Git, GitHub, threading, async programming, low latency services, object-oriented design, debugging	

Other Skills/Experience

- Technical writing (documentation, training materials); presenting/training (have spoken at several conferences); blogging
- Software project management; personnel management; team building
- Sales and account management; consulting; technology evangelism
- Broad professional and social interests; diverse cultural experience; avid student of technology and history
- Many part-time technology/finance consulting engagements over the years: financial product design, cash flow modelling, risk
 analysis, technical architecture; various meetings/presentations at the US Fed and the US/UK Treasury on different initiatives

Education

9/1989 – 6/1992:	St. John's College, Oxford University – B. A. Honours, Mathematics	Oxford, UK

Miscellaneous

Dual national (UK/US). Interests: Playing guitar (blues, rock); repairing/hacking guitars/amps; music technology; scouting (assistant scout master for local troop, Wood Badge N2-72-17); Aikido; mathematics; puzzles; electronics; wood working; blogging